<?xml version="1.0" encoding="System"?>
<table>
  <name>outlines</name>
  <rows>
    <row>
      <value column="0">1</value>
      <value column="1">Rediscovering the Original Intent and Purpose of the Church</value>
      <value column="2">Eph 3:1-12, Rev 21:9-11, 14-16, 1 Tim 3:15</value>
      <value column="3">To raise a disclaimer to what has erroneously been taught and sustained over time to be the purpose of the Church;To help us rediscover and present to us the original purpose of God for instituting the Church;To make every individual believer understand that regardless of our colour, language and background, we’ve only got a unified purpose in Christ.</value>
      <value column="4"><![CDATA[The key to understanding humankind’s purpose and essence on earth is to understand God’s original intent for why He institutionalized the church. If we know what God intended in His program for us the Church, then we can better appreciate our God -ordained obligations and know His expectations over our lives as this awareness invariably translates to instil and stir up a deep sense of purpose and responsibility in us.
            Therefore, to start with, intent can be defined as original purpose. If the intent of a thing is not well defined, misunderstanding and abuse are inevitable. This is why this present study is pivotal to bringing us to the very intent of God for His Church. 
            Suffice to say that the misconception of God’s original intent for humankind is what has resulted in the inception of several religions across the globe. Men in search of their true essence outside of Christ is what has translated to the birthing of several religions on a large scale. Religion is only a man’s idea, not God’s. God never intended His purpose for the Church to be guessed or self -coined, rather He spelt it out upfront even before the creation of man and that was what became His motivation for the creation of man. 
            God has not left us in the dark as to what His intent for the Church was and is. And this, he has clearly stated in Genesis 1:26 and Eph 3:10-11as follows:
            Gen.1.26 - And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.
            Eph.3:10-11; To the intent that now unto the principalities and powers in heavenly places might be known by the church the manifold wisdom of God, according to the eternal purpose which he purposed in Christ Jesus our Lord.
            In other words, God’s design was to extend His Kingly rule from Heaven to Earth. He purposed to extend His invisible heavenly kingdom to the Earth through the rulership of His children (i.e. the universal body of Christ). 
            Historically, whenever the rulers of a kingdom or empire have desired to expand its influence or territory, they have done so primarily by one of these two kingdom - expansion strategies: ‘outright conquest’ or ‘colonization’. Outright conquest refers to the process by which a kingdom that seeks to expand its territorial influence invades a foreign territory by her armies whereby the people are enslaved and taken away from their own country to the home territory of the conquering power. On other hand, colonization is simply defined as the extension of a kingdom in a foreign territory impacting it with its purpose, will, intent and values until that territory takes on the culture and character of the kingdom where the so -impacted territory is called colony. Unlike the kingdom expansion strategy by outright conquest, God’s original idea to extend His heavenly kingdom to earth was preferably by colonization. In other words, God’s original purpose was to make Earth a colony of Heaven by the rulership of His appointed cabinet (the Church).
            The word ‘Church’ which in Hebrew transliteration is the word ‘Ecclesia’ means ‘called out ones’ or ‘assembly of citizens in a city-state’. It was the same term used for the Roman Emperor Caesar’s cabinet instituted to carry out his injunctions in the empire. The Ecclesia of the Roman Emperor had a single obligation, to enforce only the decrees and biddings of  Caesar and to represent his intent in every colony of the empire. 
            In the same vein, God has called the church out of the dark world into His Kingdom of light and appointed us to represent Him to the world and demonstrate His multifaceted wisdom in all of its entire infinite varieties and innumerable aspects to the angelic rulers and authorities (principalities and powers) in the heavenly sphere. Remarkable! 
            It was to this end, God created the first man, Adam and that made him the first church that ever existed in time. He was created with a mandate to exercise dominion over the earth, but then along the line, he failed in his roles as a father (which in Hebrew translates ‘Abba’ meaning a protector, provider and cultivator) and a husband (which in Hebrew translates ‘ish’ meaning a house band) and as result declared his independence of God’s government. Adam’s sin was what our contemporary rule of law will call ’treason’ the crime of betraying one’s country and the values embodied in the country’s constitutional system and it is a crime punishable by death (which was exactly what happened to Adam and all of mankind - spiritual death).
            However, all thanks to God for His redemptive work through Christ Jesus by shedding His blood, the forgiveness of our sins according to the abundance of His grace and love that all men might be restored to God and His original purpose for their existence.
            ]]>
      </value>
      <value column="5" null="true"></value>
      <value column="6">In essence, God desires to extend His heavenly kingdom on earth through I and you. And so it becomes imperative of each and every one of us to let down our personal interests, and embrace in the spirit of oneness the God -ordained purpose for us the church and to know by the instrumentality of the Holy Spirit what sphere of influence God will have every one of us to represent His kingdom. This is our individual and unified purpose in Christ! 
      </value>
      <value column="7" null="true"></value>
      <value column="8" null="true"></value>
      <value column="9">I choose to be emptied of personal interests and to embrace God -ordained purpose. I know my place by destiny allotment and I have all that is required to profit the kingdom. I choose to represent God to my sphere of  influence and demonstrate a definite dimension of His wisdom to the principalities and powers as He has purposed according to His eternal counsel. Amen. Glory halleluyah!</value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">2</value>
      <value column="1">The Present State and the Intending State of the Church
      </value>
      <value column="2">Eph 3:7-12, 1 Cor 1:1-7,10-13; 3:1-5</value>
      <value column="3">To know how the church has deviated from its intended purpose.;To understand the intended church and present church.;To call back the church to her original intent.
      </value>
      <value column="4"><![CDATA[It’s no longer hidden how for the body of Christ has deviated over the years from the intended image as revealed in the word of God.this is largely due to the fact that the church has been beclouded by contemporary traditions of Men, inordinate criticism of ministers of the gospel, materialism,doctrinal difference at the expense of the church’s growth.
                            Ideally, God intended for the church to influence the world system by the values of the kingdom through the agency of the church by a partnership with the instrumentality of the holy spirit. On the contrary, the world has largely influenced the church by its system thereby causing the church to celebrate a life of average & mediocrity. Although the church is growing on the revelation knowledge of Christ, this has not seemed to affect the civic society she seeks to sharpen as intended by God. According to Eph 3:10, it is the intention of God for the church to demonstrate its multifaceted wisdom to the angelic rules & power in the heavenly and this is the Hallmark of the balanced church we seek to reflect.
            ]]>      </value>
      <value column="5">1. From what you’ve observed over time, how can you explain the present church compared to the church intended by God according to Eph 3:10.
            2. Highlight the roles of the church of God as Intended by God (Eph 6:18-21, Acts1:8, Matt 28:18-20, Jam 5:14, Acts 15:1-22, Matt 5:13-16, Act 13:1-4)
            3. With practical examples discuss how the church has deviated from the original purpose of God.
            4. How can the gap between The Present State and the Intended state of the church be bridged? (Rev 2:2-5, 19-26; 3:1-3, 15-19)
      </value>
      <value column="6">God requires the church to represent his government on earth and to serve as an ambassador of heaven influencing the world system by the values of the kingdom.</value>
      <value column="7"> Since each believer has a responsibility to demonstrate the wisdom of God, what dimension of God’s wisdom have you revealed to your world?</value>
      <value column="8">‘The glory of this latter temple shall be greater than the former’ says the Lord of hosts. ‘And in this place, I will give peace,’ says the Lord of hosts. ‘The People Are Defiled’</value>
      <value column="9" type="1">Dear Lord, we declare that despite the present state of the Church, by the force of Your glory, we arise above every limitation and we take our rightful place as the Lighthouse of the cosmos. The Spirit of God keeps brooding on us until we reflect the very ideal picture in the mind of God which is Jesus Christ. We believe that you are working in us both to will and to do of your good pleasure. Therefore, together as one body of Christ, we arise as a living witness to all that the Godhead represents, spreading the fragrance of Jesus Christ across all walks of life and penetrating every nook and cranny of the spheres of human influence with the values and belief systems of the kingdom until the whole earth is filled the knowledge of the glory of God as the waters cover the sea.  Amen!</value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">3</value>
      <value column="1">The Law of Process: Building Spiritual Capacity</value>
      <value column="2">Col 2:6-8, Jude 1:17-20, Matt 26:40-41, 1Tim 4:7-8</value>
      <value column="3">To help us understand the importance of spiritual capacity.; To make us understand the various ways of how we can constantly and consciously build spiritual capacity.; To help us know the essence of building spiritual capacity as an individual and as a church.</value>
      <value column="4">Spiritual capacity is the measure of the ability of an individual to understand, contain and host the realities of the kingdom.
            	Building spiritual capacity is the conscious act of developing the ability to accommodate certain truth and realities in God that if engaged would reproduce attendant results.
            	It is, therefore, expected of us as an individual and as a church to constantly build capacity in the spirit as the move of God in time requires a certain measure of truth and energy before it can be birthed and experienced (Acts 1:12-14, 2:1-4). The church will remain barren of spiritual realities and keep celebrating mediocrity until she takes up the responsibility of consciously building spiritual capacity to the end that the kingdom of God might find its expression through His sons on earth.
            	God is a limitless and multidimensional being, therefore man cannot know all of God at once hence, the need to consciously and consistently build a system around our daily knowing of Him. This is how we have our spiritual senses exercised and sharpened, and our spirit man energised in discerning and enforcing the mind of God (Heb 5:14).
      </value>
      <value column="5">1. a. What do you understand by spiritual capacity?
            b. Why should a believer build spiritual capacity? (Col 2:6-8)
            2. Discuss the following as ways of building the capacity
            a. As a believer
            i. Consistent prayer life (Jude 1:20, Eph 6:8, Luke 18:1)
            ii. Making fasting a habit (Matt 4:1-2, Matt 17:19-21)
            iii. Cultivating the habit of studying the word (Col 3:16, Acts 20:22, Josh 1:8, Psa 119:97-100)
            (iv) Reading of spiritual books (Dan 9:2, 2Tim 2:15)
            (v) Daily dying to the flesh (1Cor 15:31, 2Cor 4:16-17)
            	
            	b. As a church
            		i. Strategic and consistent prayer pattern (Acts 4:23-24,31, Acts 13:1-3)
            		ii. Effective administration of the fivefold ministry (quality leadership) (Eph 4:11-14, John 21:17)
            		iii. Teaching sound doctrine and continuing thereof (Titus 1:9, 2Tim 1:13)
            		(iv) Fellowshipping with the brethren (Heb 10:24:25, Gal 6:1)
            
            	3. Discuss the following as the importance of investing in spiritual things
            	i. Spiritual strength (Matt 26:40-41, Eph 3:14-19, 2Cor 2:16-17)
            	ii. Spiritual stability (Eph 4:14, 13:9, Col 2:6-7)
            	iii. Boldness to represent God in sphere of influence (Dan 2:49, 1Sam 17:45-47, Esth 4:16)
            
            	4. Why do believers find it difficult to invest in spiritual things?
            	5. Practically explain how a man of spiritual capacity can effectively represent God in the arms of government: Executive, Legislative and Judiciary.
      </value>
      <value column="6">The level at which a believer can effectively and strategically represent God in the sphere of human influence will only be a function of how much of God and his realities that he has embodied.</value>
      <value column="7">The extent to which a believer can enforce the governing influence of the kingdom on earth is not a function of mere words but sufficient spiritual capacity. Therefore, if there is any time when we should start building spiritual capacity to profit the kingdom of God, there is no better time than NOW!!!</value>
      <value column="8">’But they that wait upon the Lord shall renew their strength; they shall mount up with wings as eagles; they shall run, and not be weary, and they shall walk, and shall not be faint.’ ’ Isaiah 40:31</value>
      <value column="9" type="2">I refuse to be a weakling in my generation,
            My strength is of the Lord,
            I choose to enforce God’s statutes on earth until this world becomes  the kingdom of God and of His Christ.</value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">4</value>
      <value column="1">The Law of Process: Built to Last!</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Col 2:6-8, Mat 16:13-19, Eph 2:19-20
      </value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To make believers aware of whom we build our faith on as a church; To show believers how to build ourselves to last as a church
      </value>
      <value column="4" null="true">To build means to establish, increase and preserve a structure after a predesigned plan. Thus, been built to last means to work on an existing bedrock such that it can last the test of time. There are two possibilities upon which a believers faith can be built; the wisdom of men and the revelation of God which is the person of Christ. Mathew 16:18, also reveals that Christ is the rock on which the church is being built such that the gate of hell - death, trials, worries, temptations can not prevail over it.</value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1. According to your understanding, what does it mean to be ‘built to last’.
      2. On what foundation should a believer build on? Why?
      3. What are the systems that have been put in place to build the church that last.
      a. Prayer - Acts 6:4, Jude 20
      b. Studying and meditating on the word of God - Acts 2:42, 20:32, Joshua 1:8, 2 Tim 3:16-17
      c. Mentorship and discipleship - Heb 13:17, Gal 4:1-2 &amp; 19, 2 Tim 3:14-15, Acts 18:24-28
      d. Kingdom services - Mark 9:35, 10:43-45
      e. Five fold ministry - Eph 4:10-12
      4. What are the dangers of building ones faith on the philosophy of men, with practical examples.
      5. What proves the foundation a believer has been building on - Mathew 6:23, 1 Cor 3:13</value>
      <value column="6">Since Christ is our chief cornerstone, if the church will be built to last, no builder should build outside the predesigned plan.
      </value>
      <value column="7">if therefore the light in you is darkness, how great is that darkness?
      </value>
      <value column="8" null="true">...each one’s work will become clear; for the Day will declare it, because it will be revealed by fire; and the fire will test each one’s work, of what sort it is. - 1 Cor 3:13, NKJV</value>
      <value column="9" null="true"></value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">5</value>
      <value column="1">The Law of Process: Knowing the Person of the Holy Spirit</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">John 14:16-20, 16:7-8, Rom 8:9, 11,13-16
      </value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To introduce the person of the Holy Spirit to us
      ; To help believers understand the essence of the Holy Spirit
      ; To help believers cultivate fellowship with the Holy Spirit
      </value>
      <value column="4" null="true">The questions ‘What/Who is the Holy Spirit’ and ‘How to cultivate a more intimate relationship with Him?’ have always been the major questions many believers ask especially believers who are just coming up in the faith. Some think of Him as a force or an influence, another as an angel or a dove because of what He was linked to in the Bible (Mathew 3:16).
      According to John 14:16, Jesus said, He will pray the Father to give another comforter which in Greek is referred to as ‘Alos Parakletos’ (which means a comforter of His kind). Knowing the significance of the Holy Spirit to a believer, He told them why He must go (John 16:7). Notice the pronouns Jesus used to describe the Holy Spirit (He and Him), this shows that the Holy Spirit is a person that has an influence. Jesus also made us knew that He proceeds from the father (John 15:26). Job described the Holy Spirit as the creator of man which further show that He is the same as God (Job 33:4, Gen 1:26, 1 John 4:7). 
      Knowing and cultivating a personal relationship with the Holy Spirit is very important to every believer if we must live an excellent and struggle free life.</value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1. The person of the Holy Spirit.
            A. What proves that the Holy Spirit is a person?
      I. He has a mind - Rom 8:27
      II. He has a will - 1 Cor 12:11
      III. He has emotion and feelings - Eph 4:30, Isaiah 63:10a
      IV. He can speak - Rev 2:29, 1 Tim 4:1, Hebrew 3:7
      2.  How do I receive the Holy Spirit and His baptism - Salvation John 1:12, Rom 10:9
      3.  The ministry of the Holy Spirit.
            A. What He ministers to us
      I. He is our advantage - 1 john 4:4, John 14:12, 16:7, 2 Cor 3:5-6
      II. Our comforter - 1 Cor 1:3, John 14:16, 26(KJV)
      III. Our helper - Rom 8:26
      IV. Our advocate - Rom 8:27
      V. Our teacher and the revealer - 1 John 2:20 &amp; 27, 1 Cor 2:10-11
      VI. Our seal of redemption and guarantee of our inheritance - Eph 1:13-14, 4:30, 2 Cor 1:22
      VII. The spirit of truth - John 14:17, 16:13
      VIII. The spirit of obedience and our companion for life - Eze 36:27, John 14:16, 18
      IX. The spirit of wisdom, understanding, counsel, might, knowledge and fear of the Lord - Isaiah 11:2
      X. Our access to the Father - Eph 2:18
      B. How He ministers to us 
      I. The word - 2 Tim 3:16-17, Heb 4:12
      II. Through conscience - Rom 9:1
      III. Vision/ Trance - Acts 10:10-13, 16:9-10, 22:17-18
      IV. Audible voice - Acts 9:4-6, 13:2-3
      V. Dreams - Acts 2:17, Matt 1:20, 2:13
      VI. Inner witness - Rom 8:16
      VII. Inner voice - Isaiah 30:21
      VIII. Peace of the mind - Phil 4:6-7
      IX. Circumstances - Acts 16:6-8(MSG)
      4)    In real -life scenarios, discuss how you’ve been led by the Holy Spirit.
      5)    Share how you have struggled with hearing the voice of the Holy Spirit and how you overcame it.
      6)     How do believers strife with the Holy Spirit? Highlight the consequences.
      7)     How do I know the Holy Spirit more?
              I. Pure desire - Psa 42:1-2, 63:1
              II. Self denial - Mathew 16:24
      III. Consistency in the place of prayer and the word - Acts 6:4, 1 Cor 15:58
      IV. Meditation - Joshua 1:8
      V. Obedience - James 1:22, John 14:23, 1 John 2:17, proverbs 10:17
      </value>
      <value column="6">The Holy Spirit is the greatest advantage of every believer, with Him is no confusion (we know what to do in every situation) and struggle. We must recognize, be conscious and obey the person of the Holy Spirit to live an effective life pleasing to God as Christians. All that we need and will ever need the Father has given to us in the Holy Spirit that lives in us. It is therefore expedient that we recognize Him as our companion in daily fellowship with His Person and let Him lead you as He ought to (submitting to Him as you would a friend that knows more than you, to teach you).</value>
      <value column="7">The extent to which you are in sync with the Holy Spirit (see Him as a person), is the degree to which you conform to His image.
      </value>
      <value column="8" null="true">But God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God. - 1 Cor 2:10</value>
      <value column="9" type="2">Dear Holy Spirit, help me to know you more and to cultivate a daily and intimate relationship with you. I yield and submit myself to your influence and I receive grace to live from now on with the consciousness of your presence on my inside all the days of my life.
      </value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">6</value>
      <value column="1">The Law of Process: Understanding the Purpose of Prayer and the Word of God</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Acts 6:4, Lk.18:1-7, Mk.4:3-20, Is.29:11-12</value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To bring us into an accurate and appropriate communication with God through effective praying; To make us understand how the word of God is pivotal to our spiritual growth and relevance in every sphere of influence</value>
      <value column="4" null=" true">It can be said that one of the most common and universal human activity on earth is prayer, yet it is one of the most misunderstood human engagements ever. Since the dawn of time right from the primitive human culture to complex civilisation around the globe, this ancient art called prayer has been known to be practised to some gods or deities. 
        Some see it as a religious ritual or simply a poor man’s invention designed as an outlet for fear, frustration, lack and anxiety or perhaps it is nothing more than some psychological exercise that eases the mind and helps to cope with life’s challenges at best. 
        Truth be told, even many among believers are suffering from a silent disillusion with our experience of this spiritual art called prayer. Typical religious folks grew to pray but never at any time enlightened why and how to pray. Some categories of believers view other believers who are committed to a lifestyle of prayer to be too religious, wasting their time practising the art.
        Even among believers who pray regularly conscious and obtain some results, it is discovered that some have silent doubts about certain aspects of prayer: for instance, why we pra, how do we pray, how long do we pray and similar questions concerning the nature of prayer.
        On the other hand, attitudes of believers to the word of God are yet from different perspectives. Some believers overrate prayer at the expense of the word of God while some do with the word at the expense of prayer. Taking either of the two above each other does not portray a balanced church that we seek to reflect.
        Jesus said in Matt 22:29 ‘Ye do err not knowing the scriptures, nor the power of God’. Hence, it is an indispensable truth that prayer and the word cam likened to the two wings of believers as one can’t fly without the other. It is worthy of note that essentially, prayer is a means of communion and fellowship with God. Other importances of prayer follow suit but it is expedient that prayer changes people before it changes things as the changed people later change things (Lk 9:29). In the same vein, the word of God is primarily a means of building a believer to become like Christ (2 Tim3:16-17, Col.3:16, Acts 20:32).
      </value>
      <value column="5" null="true">A. ON PRAYER
        1. From the following references, discuss how the characters cultivated an effective prayer culture and how we can learn from them.
        a. Sam 1 Sam 12:23
        b. Elijah 1 Kings 18:42-44, James 5:16-17
        c. Paul 1 Thess3:10, Eph.3:14-16
        d. Jesus Christ (our perfect example). Lk.5:9:29, Mk.1:35
        2. Why pray?
        i. Fellowship and communion with God. Ps.63:1, 42:1-2
        ii. Knowing God’s will for our lives and in every situation of life. Jer.33:3, 42:2-3, Dan.2:16-19
        III. Building up of believers. Jude 20, 1 Cor 14:4
        iv. Kingdom advancement. Acts 4:29, Hab.2:14, Matt.6:9-10
        v. Spiritual enlightenment. Jer.33:3, Eph.1:15-18
        vi. Spiritual understanding,  fruitfulness and increase in the knowledge of God. Col.1:9-10, Phil.1:9-11
        3. How to pray?
        I. Praying in the name of Jesus. John 14:14, Col.3:17, Acts 3:6
        ii. Praying by faith. Acts 3:16, Mk.11:24, Heb.11:6, Matt.21:22, James 1:6-18
        III. Praying with desire and hunger. Prov 18:1, Ps.63:1-2, 42:1-2, Jer 29:13
        iv. Praying in the Spirit (i.e. praying in tongues). Acts 2:4, 1 Cor 14:18, Eph.6:18
        v. Praying in understanding within the context of God’s will. 1 Cor 14:15
        4. Discuss the following kinds of prayer
        I. Prayer of thanksgiving. Eph.5:20, 1 Thess5:18, Col.3:17
        ii. Prayer of petitions. James 1:5-8, Mk.11:24
        iii. Prayer of intercession. 1 Tim2:1-2, Jer.27:18, Is.59:16, Ex.32:30-32
        iv. Prayer of consecration. Matt.26:39, Acts 13:2
        v. Prayer of agreement. Matt.18:19, Acts 12:5, 4:23
        vi. Prayer by the Spirit (i.e. groaning in the Spirit). Rom.8:26, Judg.6:34
        5. Why do believers struggle in the place of prayer and highlight practical remedies to them.
        i. Posture of the heart (i.e. wrong motives, the distraction of the soul, unrenewed mind etc) James 4:3,8, Matt.5:8, 1 John 3:21, Ps.139:23-24a, Lk.18:9-14
        ii. Lack of desire and hunger. Jer.29:13, Prov.18:1, Heb.5:17
        iii. Identity crisis (lack of consciousness of who we are in Christ). Lk.9:54-55, Rom.5:1, Eph.2:13, Heb.4:16, 1 Jn1:9,2:2
        iv. Hasteness in the place of prayer (lack of praying power). Eccl.8:3, Is.40:31, Hab.2:1
        v. Shortcomings of flaws. Mk.11:25-26, Matt.18:21-35
        vi. Discouragement as a resultant effect of unanswered prayers. 1 Sam1:8-10
        vi. Not recognizing the place of the Holy Spirit in helping our infirmities to pray. Rom.8:26-27, Ps.80:18
        B. ON THE WORD OF GOD
        6. Why study the word of God.
        i. Communion and fellowship. 2 Cor 3:18
        ii. Spiritual enlightenment into the operation of God’s system. Ps.119:18, Acts 16:14
        iii. Knowing the will of God for our lives and in every situation of life. Job.29:3-4
        iv. Renewing of our mind and sustaining the mind of Christ in every area of our lives. Rom.12:2, Eph.4:23, Ps.119:97-100
        v. Guidance and direction for life. Ps.119:105, Eph.4:23
        vi. Refraining from evil and sin, and knowing and inculcating the values and culture of the Kingdom. Ps.119:101-102, 1 Tim4:15-16, 3:16-17
        vii. Prosperity and good success in every area of life. Job 1:8
        7. How to study the word?
        i. Reading 
        ii. In -depth study 
        iii. Comparing scriptures with scriptures
        iv. Meditation
        v. Using supporting aids to enhance our understanding of the word
        vi. Memorization and confession of scriptures 
        8. ‘A balanced believer does not overrate prayer at the expense of the word and vice versa’. Justify this statement. John 15:7
      </value>
      <value column="6">Any believer who will grow up spiritually in Christ and be relevant to the society will be such that embraces both the word and prayer equally. These are the two elements that make up a believer. </value>
      <value column="7">It is not just enough to know that prayer and the word are important, the question is are you faithful to this daily?</value>
      <value column="8" null="true">Acts.6.4 - ‘But we will give ourselves continually to prayer, and to the ministry of the word’</value>
      <value column="9" type="2">Dear Father, I’m yielded to be built, edified, energised and strengthened by your word and prayer for a life of greatness, victory and triumphs. Through the ministry of the Word, and prayer by the instrumentality of the Holy Spirit, my growth - spiritually, physically, academically, mentally, emotionally, financially, maritally and career -wise becomes evident; there’s an outburst of prosperity in every area of my life, to the praise and glory of your name. Amen.
      </value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">7</value>
      <value column="1">The Law of Process: The Renewing of the Mind</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Eph 4:17-24, Rom 12:1-2, 2Corin 4:16
      </value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To help us understand the importance of continual renewing of the mind; To understand how we can renew our mind; To show the danger of an unrenewed mind</value>
      <value column="4" null=" true">The mind is regarded as the seat of intellect, will and emotion which coordinates a man’s behaviour either towards a positive lifestyle or a negative one. After the fall, the heart of man became evil bringing enmity between man and God (Gen 6:5, Jere 17:9). The redemptive work of Christ by the love of God brought man to his original position (Rom 5:8, Jhn 3:16). However, the mind, being the basis for transformation, needs to be renewed through conscious responsibility in beholding Christ if we are to be changed from glory to glory (2Corin3:18). The level of a man’s transformation is the degree to which he has renewed his mind, therefore for the Church to truly reflect the intent of God, it is expedient of us to subject our mind to continuous renewal.</value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1. What do you understand by the renewing of the mind
            2. Why should we renew our mind (Rom 12:1-2,Jn 8:31-32,Col 3:16, Mtw 22:29,31,Hos 4:6)
            3. Discuss the following as a way by which we can renew our mind 
            i. Consistent studying and meditation on the word (1Tim 4;15,Heb 4:12, Philipians 4:8,Pslm 119:11,Col 3:16, Eph 4:20-24) 
            ii. Consistent prayer life (Luk 18:1, 1Thes 5:17,Jude 1:20, Acts 10:13,14,28,29)
            iii. Christian books (Dan 9:2, 2Tim 4:13,Ezra 7:10) 
            iv. Consciously engaging in positive confession (Rom 10:10,2Corin4:13,Prov18:21)
            v. Constructive teaching (Acts 18:11, Rom 10:17,Col 1:28,Lam3:24(MSG))
            vi. Regular fellowshipping with the brethren (Heb 10:25 )
            vii. Keeping godly company (1Corin 15:33,Prov13:20,2Corin 6:14-16b)
            4. Discuss the following as the benefits of renewing our mind 
            i. Spiritual stability (Eph 4:14, Col 2:6-8, Mtw 7:24-25)
            ii. Courage and confidence (2Tim 2:15)
            iii. It helps us live a victorious life (Dan 2:46-48,6:1-3)
            iv. Proving the will of God (Eph 5:17, Rom 12:2)
            v. Grace and peace (2pet 1:2-3)
            5. Explain the following as the dangers of an unrenewed mind 
            i. Carnality (Rom 8:5-8)
            ii. Wrong decision making (Num 20:8,11-12,Gen 25:29-34,1king 12:6-8,19-28)
            iii. Reprobacy and deprivation (Rom 1:28) 
            iv. Hyprocracy (Mark 7:6-9,1Tim 4:2) 
            v. Spiritual blindness (Eph 4:18, Jn 9:39-41)
            vi. Hardship (Hos 4:6, Isaiah 5:13)
      </value>
      <value column="6">The mind is no doubt the seat that controls life’s physical, ’soulical’ and spiritual manifestation. It’s therefore expedient of us to constantly subject our mind to the dealings of the Holy Spirit unto good works to the glory of God through the knowledge of Christ Jesus our Lord.
      </value>
      <value column="7">A man cannot be transformed beyond the level to which he has renewed his mind. 
      </value>
      <value column="8" null="true">Eph 4:23-24 - ‘And be renewed in the spirit of your mind and that you put on the new man which after God is created in righteousness and true holiness’</value>
      <value column="9" null="true">By the power of the Holy Spirit, I cast off worthless and unproductive thoughts, and use my mind correctly to picture the glorious and victorious life that I have in Christ. Henceforth, I choose to be selective of the kind of information I expose my mind to and consciously think upon and focus on the spiritual realities of the Word, and project myself to greater levels of success, prosperity and victory. Amen.</value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">8</value>
      <value column="1">The Law of Process: Understanding the Principle and Purpose of Proper Mentorship and Discipleship</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Acts 14:22, 18:26, Matt.4:19, Lk.9:23, Mk.3:14</value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To make us understand how indispensable discipleship and mentorship are in perpetuating the ordinance of God on earth; To make us understand the need for discipleship and mentorship in becoming all that God has created us to be on earth.</value>
      <value column="4" null="true">God’s way of making believers be conformed to the image of the Lord Jesus Christ is what is referred to as discipleship. In other words, discipleship is a systemic and cumulative process of imparting knowledge and life to a disciple (follower). 
        On the other hand, mentorship is a process of transferring knowledge, values, ideals, social capital perceived by the recipient as relevant to work, career, marriage, finances or professional development usually face -to -face and during a constant period of time between a person who is perceived to have greater relevant knowledge or experience (the mentor) and the person who is perceived to have less (the protege/mentee).
        It is incumbent to know that the new birth in Christ Jesus is what ushers us into an inheritance in God (Col 1:12). However, lack of spiritual growth robs us of possessing the inheritance we have obtained in Christ. To attain spiritual growth, God’s way of moulding His children and conforming them to the image of His son is by discipleship (Gal.4:1,19).
        Since the scope of Christianity is not limited to the church horizon, but to extend the governing influence of the Kingdom values into a succeeding generation to perpetuate the ordinance of God on earth. 
        The greatest accomplishment in leadership is not an immediate success, but succession. Thus, succession refers to the effective transfer, conveyance and transition of the leader’s purpose, vision, passion, intents, character, standards, morals, values and qualities to a succeeding generation of leaders.</value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1. What do you understand by these pairs of statements:  ‘a discipler and a disciple’ and ‘a mentor and a mentor’?
        2. How would you compare and contrast discipleship and mentorship?
        3. Why the need for discipleship and mentorship?
        A. Discipleship 
        i. Conformity to the image of Christ. Rom.8:29
        ii. Infusing the life and the character of the discipler (Jesus) to the disciple. Acts 11:26, 4:13
        B. Mentorship
        i. Nurturing innate abilities of and instilling cardinal values into the recipient 
        ii. Shaping the trajectory of the recipient with real -life experience of the mentor
        iii. A proven system of bringing the best version of the mentee out to the limelight.
        iv. To receive guidance in making sensitive decisions.
        v. Succession (raising another set of leaders to perpetuate success).
        vi. To live and lead a life of excellence on a sustainable basis in various walks of life.
        vii. To challenge a life of average and mediocrity in every area of life 
        4. Practically discuss the following areas and walks of life in which one should be mentored to live and lead a life of relevance and lasting impacts.
        i. Academics
        ii. Career, business and creative arts
        iii. Finances
        iv. Relationship and marriage
        v. Ministry 
        vi. Health 
        vii. Public speaking and writing skills
        5. Discuss the following qualities in identifying a discipler and a mentor.
        A. Discipler.
        i. Must be a person under the government of the Christ 1 Cor 11:1
        ii. Must depict an exemplary life. 1 Tim4:12
        iii. Must be a person of strong character.
        iv. Must be a person of good reputation
        B. Mentor
        i. Extensive experience in a related field 
        ii. Must have overcome relatable challenges
        iii. Must be able to see potentials within the mentee more than he sees in himself 
        iii. Friendly and genuine personality
        iv. Credible and trustworthy character
        v. Must not feel threatened or insecure by empowering others
        vi. Must be able to invest quality time in the mentee and must be considerably accessible at every time of need and favourably disposed to flexible mentoring style.
        vii. Must possess a listening ear and be open enough to learn from the mentee.
        6. What should be the attitude of a disciple and a mentee?
        i. Must be eager and open to learn 
        ii. Must be submissive to the mentor
        iii. Must have a sense of purpose and responsibility towards the mentorship and discipleship programme
        iii. Must endeavour to always maintain effective communication with the mentor
        iv. Must be apt to ask questions on things not cleared about and possessing a spirit of inquisitive
        v. Must always honour the mentor whether in his/her presence or absence
      </value>
      <value column="6">The greatest leader of all times (Jesus Christ) invested three and a half years of His life not in erecting physical structures or accruing wealth, but in building people. No wonder His set course would still be standing for the next 2000 years  
        Kindly note that there is no such thing as being self -made, every great man and woman you see today or in time past has or had a mentor/ a discipler. It is amazing how the 21st -century generation has lost this indispensable art of being mentored by models with proven life in ministry and career because we think we have known too much to be mentored, yet we hope to be relevant and make impacts in our world, how can that ever be possible! A mentor is simply a reflection of one’s future, so the question is who is your mentor? It is high time we swallowed our pride and prayerfully and wisely identify a mentor and a discipler.
      </value>
      <value column="7">The hallmark of leadership is not in building buildings, but in building people! What are you building? </value>
      <value column="8" null="true">1 Cor 11:1 - ‘Imitate me, just as I imitate Christ’
      </value>
      <value column="9" type="2">Dear Father, open my eyes to see whom you’ve appointed to build and groom me in bringing the best version of me out and to become a perfect reflection of your intentions for my life in every area - spiritually, academically, financially, mentally, emotionally, maritally and career -wise. Now that I have known whom you’ve appointed for my building, cause grace to be multiplied to me to ever committed to this life -transforming art and help me to possess a heart of teachability and a spirit of submissiveness so that in the long run I will be nothing short of your purpose for my life.</value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">9</value>
      <value column="1">The Law of Empowerment: Development of Virtues - Strong Character</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Gal 5:14-26, 2 Pet 1:3-9, Phil 4:8</value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To understand the nature of Christ; To know why virtue is needed in the development of strong character; To know its importance in the growth of the church </value>
      <value column="4" null="true">The building of a complete Church involves the development of believers in all aspects including character. Virtue is a strong inner disposition and a disposition is the tendency to act in certain ways (Luke 6:45). Virtue can also be described as the presence of the fruit of the Spirit made manifest (Gal 5:22-23). It is otherwise referred to as moral excellence and goodness. The nature of Christ is what distinguishes a believer with a strong character from an unbeliever including the moralists among them. 
      Since God has called us into glory and virtue, it is therefore expedient for a believer to add to their faith; virtues and to continually abound in them without which fruitfulness cannot be attained.</value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1) What are virtues? (Discuss in relation to character building) 2 Pet 1:3-9 
      2) Why do we need to develop strong character? 
        - It is God’s instruction (2 Pet 1:3) 
        - Fruitfulness (2 Pet 1:8, John 15:8 )
        - It builds the church (Acts 2:46-47)
        - It makes the church relevant in the society (Dan 6:3) 
      3) Explain the following qualities and how they build strong characters in a believer.
          - Virtue 
          - Knowledge 
          - Self -control / Temperance
          - Perseverance/ Patience 
          - Godliness 
          - Brotherly Kindness 
          - Love / charity 
      4)i. Which of these characters are believers not portraying?
         ii. How has the failure of the church to portray these characters affected the family, community, government and the nation at large?
         iii. What are the practical steps to take to correct the anomaly in the church?
          - Constructive teaching (Titus 2:15) 
          - Godly parenting (2 Tim 1:5) 
          - Self examination (2 Cor 13:5 )
          - Helping those who fall short of the fold (Gal 6:1)
          - Competent leadership (1 Tim 3 vs 8, Titus 1:7-9)
          - Diligence (2 Pet 1:5)
      The Bible speaks expressly concerning what things a believer should add to his faith, which are self -control, Godliness, love, knowledge, affections. This makes full proof of our calling and shows us as a light to the world. 
      </value>
      <value column="6">The Genotype in a Man is fully noticed in his Phenotype suffice to say that a Man with God as his Father must reflect God in his actions and physique.</value>
      <value column="7">Anointing shakes the world, character sharpens the world. 
      </value>
      <value column="8" null="true">Phil 4:9a - ‘those things, which ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and seen in me, do’ 
      </value>
      <value column="9" null="true">I am a Son of God. I have the Righteousness of God in me </value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">10</value>
      <value column="1">The Law of Empowerment: The Law of Honour and Submission</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Gen 16:5-10, Num 12:1-15, 1 Sam 2:30, Rom 13:1-7</value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To make us understand what it really means by honour and submission; To make us know the essence of honour and submission in the Kingdom.</value>
      <value column="4" null="true">God’s works issue from God’s throne and His throne is established upon authority. All things have been created by the authority of God and all laws on earth are held together by authority. The Bible reveals to us that God upholds all things by the Word, which is of His authority (Heb 1:3b). Honour, therefore, can be defined as the discerning, recognition, celebration and rewarding of excellence, usefulness, values and graces. While dishonour means to lightly esteem and takes things (values, excellence and graces) or people for granted.
      In the kingdom, there are three major cores to which honour can be accorded: God, Men and Principles as would be seen shortly in the course of the study. The kingdom of God operates on the system of honour while the kingdom of darkness operates on the system of self -exaltation. Dishonour is largely seen in our generation today due to the lack of discernment of graces in men and delegated authority set over us. This has posed a lot of limitations to the advancement and furtherance of God’s agenda in our days as the less is always blessed of the greater. 
      The limitation of the younger generation is that they strive at their own pace to achieve what can only be inherited by honour and submission from the older generation.  In a bit not to recognize and honour graces in the custodians, the younger generation often misses out on God’s blessings and the heritage from the older generation, and as a result, heaps upon themselves a life full of struggles and hardship in a vicious cycle as the principles of God can not be broken. This is why a man can never rise in life beyond the level of his honour just as he can not honour beyond the level of his discerning of values, excellence and graces. 
      As it is if true saying, the secret of the future is in the past as buttressed in Prov 22:28 which reads ‘remove not the ancient landmark, which thy fathers have set’. How instructive! The gradient of transference from the fathers to the succeeding generation can only be effected on the premise of honour and submission as the kingdom can be likened to a pyramid where flow is made possible from the upper region to the lower region only through the law of honour and submission!
      </value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1. Discuss the following characters with respect to the law of honour and submission.
      a. Hagar to Sarah. Gen 16:5-10
      b. Mariam and Aaron to Moses. Num 12:1-15
      c. David to Saul 1 Sam 24:3-7
      d. Paul to Peter, James and John (the pillars of the apostleship). Gal 1:18-19, 2:7-9
      2. According to the Kingdom, there are three cores to whom honour should be accorded as listed below. Discuss how this applies in each case.
      i. God 1 Sam 2:30, Prov 3:9
      ii. Men. Lk 18:4, Eph 6:1, Heb 7:7, Matt 10:41
      iii. Principles. Prov 13:13, Gen 8:22
      3. Why do believers find it difficult to exemplify the law of honour and submission even in critical situations?
      a. Pride 1 sam 15:17, Dan 4:30-34, Acts 12:21-23 
      b. Rebellion 1 Sam 15:22-23, Ps 68:6
      c. Lack of discernment of graces and values. 1 kings 4:9, 1 Cor 11:29-30
      d. Being puffed up by knowledge. 1 Cor 8:1-2
      4. Explain how the law of honour and submission applies directly to the following delegated authorities and even vice -versa.
      i. Children to parents. Eph 6:1-3
      ii. Apprentice to master. Eph 6:4-5
      iii. Wives to husbands. Eph 5:22
      iv. Spiritual son to father. 1 Cor 4:15
      v. Congregation to shepherd. Heb 13:17, 1 Thess 5:17
      vi. Citizens to government. Rom 13:1-7
      </value>
      <value column="6">All failures in life without any exemption can be traced to dishonour either to God, men or principles. In the same vein, every success in life can be traced to honour to either of the three cores or a combination of any of them. This is why there is no failure for any man who understands and exemplifies the law of honour and honour. In applying what you have learnt so thus in this study, check any area of your life you have been struggling with and sincerely identify what exact core(s) out of the three you have dishonoured. Admit your faults and sincerely make amends at once to honour what core(s) in your life - (God, men and principles) has(have) to be honoured and watch how your life will dramatically experience an unimaginable lifting and ease. This is spiritual intelligence!</value>
      <value column="7">The Law of attraction states that anything you despise and dishonour will diminish in your life and anything you celebrate and honour will multiply in your life - be it God, men, graces, knowledge, excellence, values, money, prosperity etc. Therefore, always celebrate values and graces whenever you see one and do this unashamedly at all times!
      </value>
      <value column="8" null="true">Heb.7.7 - And without all contradiction the less is blessed of the better
      </value>
      <value column="9" type="2">Dear Father, I obtain mercy for every dishonour I have made to You, to men and your principles. I forbid the foul spirit of pride and dishonour and I declare I am humble despite my achievements and impacts in life. Henceforth, I receive grace to sincerely honour You and all the delegated authorities you have placed over me without any exemption. My eyes are open to recognize custodians of graces, values and excellence that my life needs and that You have positioned at every strategic area of my life to bless and lift me up.  Amen!

      </value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">11</value>
      <value column="1">The Church and the Society: Shaping History through Kingdom Values Systems</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Isa 2:1-5, Dan 3:28-29, Matt 5:13-16
      </value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To understand what kingdom value system is 
                      ; To understand how to promote the kingdom value system 
                      ; To understand how to sustain God’s value system for generations
      </value>
      <value column="4" null="true">God is not just a spirit that exists in a space or in his own realm, he is a king of his own government and this government has rules, order and way of life. There is a way every citizen and entity under the jurisdiction of God’s rule should operate, this is because they are governed by a value system that is established by God Himself. God’s (kingdom) value system is the body of principles, conducts and laws that guides the way of life of those under the authority of God. This value system reveals what is highly esteemed in God and the promotion of the character of God in the lives of people under the influence of God. The kingdom value system includes the incorporation of how God thinks, does His things and what God desires in the spirits and mindsets of His people. We live in a world where corruption, terrorism, materialism, hooliganism, self -aggrandizement, fraudulence, sexual perversion, moral decadence and other forms of unrighteousness are prevalent. Only God’s value system can bring order! The implementation of how heaven does its things and coordinates affairs (value system) is the only way out. This can only be effected on earth when God’s people understand the value system of God and are willing to institutionalize it in the systems of this world. Until we promote God’s value system on earth, the forces of darkness will keep running the show.
      </value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1) What are the elements in God’s value system? 
        ▪️Righteousness, peace and Joy - Prov 13:34, Rom 14:17, Rom 1:18, Isaiah 12:3
        ▪️Holiness and Purity - Heb 12:14, Psa 47:8, Matt 5:8, 
        ▪️Love - 1 John 4:12, 16, Rom 5:8, Matt 22:37
        ▪️ Unity - John 10:30, John 17:21, Psa 133:1, Eph 4:3, 13
        ▪️Obedience - 1 Sam 15:22, proverbs 8:32, Isaiah 48:12,18
        ▪️Fear of God and worship - John 4:23-24, Matt 4:9-10, Prov 9:10
        ▪️Selflessness - 1 Cor 10:24, John  7:18, Matt 22:39
        ▪️Life and health - Deut 30:19, John 10:10, John 3:16, 1 Pet 2:24
        ▪️Justice - Leviticus 19:15, Psa 98:9, Rev 19:2
        ▪️Good Character - Rom 13:12-14, Phil 4:8, 
        ▪️ Honor and respect - Exo 20:12, 1 Pet 2:17, Eph 6:1-3
        2) How can we implement these values on earth?
       a. To personally imbibe it and become one with it  - Heb 12:14, 1 Cor 15:58, Psa 119:11, Job 31:1, Prov 4:7 
       b. to demonstrate it and show it openly. 1 Thess 3:7-10,   1 Cor 2:4, Matt 5:16
       c. Through Leadership. Jeremiah 3:15, Prov 22:6, Titus 1:5-9
       d. Unwavering conviction and strong desire. Eph 4:14, Esth 4:16, Eph 6:13-18, Heb 11:13,  2 Tim 1:12
        3) How can we sustain the kingdom value system for many generations?
       a. Through constructive and consistent teachings. Matt 28:18-20, Jer.3:15, Gen 18:19, Acts 18:11, 19:8-10
        b. Quality discipleship and mentorship.  2 Tim 2:2, Acts 18:24-27, 1 Cor 4:15, 11:1, , Gal 4:19
       c. Intercession and supplication. Col 4:12-13, 1 Tim 2:1-3
       d. Spiritual warfare. Eph 6:10-18
       e. Finance and prosperity. Zech 1:17, Phil 4:19, Luke 16:9-12
      </value>
      <value column="6">The saints must first understand and then imbibe the value system of God, and ensure they reflect them strategically in government, business, entertainment, religion, education, media, family, cultures, technology and every sphere of human endeavour. Religion has prevailed for too long, it is time to instil righteousness and God’s values (belief system) in every stratum of life. It will come by salvation, preaching the gospel, demonstrating God’s power, wisdom and love. Every believer must be mindful of this and trust God for the strategies to implement this in families, institutions and societies.
      </value>
      <value column="7">If you don’t understand the value system of God, you can’t implement it. If you understand it and you take no steps, you can’t still establish it. Only the doers of the word we subdue nations and profit the kingdom!</value>
      <value column="8" null="true">Mat 28:19 Go you therefore, and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost:
      </value>
      <value column="9" null="true">The light of God will spread through me in my environment. I receive grace to bring men into the obedience of God’s way of life
      </value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">12</value>
      <value column="1">The Church and the Society: Redefining Leadership</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Col 1:15-18, Acts 6:1-7, Luke 22:24-27</value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To help us understand what true leadership means.;To help us understand that Christ should be the basis for leadership in the society.;To help understand God’s expectations on leadership.</value>
      <value column="4" null="true">Leadership can best be explained as the capacity to direct and influence others in a particular field or institution towards a noble cause. Leadership began from the first family and ever since then, through the ages, has evolved into multiple systems. 
            History reveals to us that the success of any institution is based on the strength of its leadership. Every nation rises or falls to the quality of its leadership. This is why God all through the ages has not relented in choosing someone not only to lead and direct His people but also to influence and impact the world at large.
            Generally, the world sees leadership as an avenue to exert power, accrue wealth and subjugate people for self -worship and personal aggrandizement contrary to God’s original layout.
            God’s idea of leadership is such that is founded on KINGDOM VALUES which sees to serve and represent the people towards achieving a set goal.   (Mark 9:35)</value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1.	Differentiate between a leader and a ruler.
            2.	Leadership is not a function of position but attitude. Discuss this attitude.
            3.	 Discuss the following criteria for choosing a godly leader in the Church and Civic society.
            a.	Competence. Dan 1:4
            b.	Sense of responsibility. 1 Kings 19:9, John 5:17
            c.	Good report, full of the Holy Spirit and wisdom. Acts 6:3
            d.	Seeks and is willing to do God’s will. Acts 13:22, Matt 17:5
            e.	Spirit -filled. Numbers 27:15-18
            4.	Discuss how the long sustained misconception of leadership has wreaked havoc in the following institutions:
            a.	Family
            b.	Church
            c.	Government
            d.	Politics
            e.	Educational sector
            f.	Arts &amp; Entertainment
            5	How can God raise a new breed of leaders out of us to correct the anomalies discussed above?
      </value>
      <value column="6">The decision of a leader impacts the people and this is exactly why leadership is sensitive. Therefore, since leadership is an influence, it should be coupled with the right mindset in our respective spheres of endeavour, fulfilling God’s mandate on earth.</value>
      <value column="7">The hallmark of true leadership is not to maintain followership but to raise another set of leaders.</value>
      <value column="8" null="true">“And He sat down, and called the twelve, and saith unto them, If any man desire to be first, the same shall be last of all, and servant of all.” - Mark 9:35 </value>
      <value column="9" null="true">BY THE FORCE OF THE GLORY OF GOD,
            I AM A MAN OF INFLUENCE.
            I CHOOSE GOD IN MY SPHERE OF INFLUENCE.
            I LEAD IN MY SPHERE OF INFLUENCE.
            I LEAD FOR THE GLORY OF THE LORD.</value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">13</value>
      <value column="1">The Church and the Society: Fundamentals of Relationship and Marriage</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Gen 2:15-25; 1Cor 7:1-16; Prov 12:26
      </value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To know how to keep and maintain Godly relationships,
      ; To rediscover the original intent and purpose of God for the institution of marriage,
      ; To help us know the respective responsibilities of the elements that make up the family.
      </value>
      <value column="4" null="true">The English dictionary defines relationship as a connection or association between two or more persons. A relationship can exist between friends (friendship), family (family relationship), colleagues at work (professional relationship) and life partner &amp; spouses (romantic relationship/marriage). A Godly relationship is a relationship that has Christ at its center.
      It is expedient of us to know that every kind of relationship has an impact upon the persons involved either negatively or positively. This is why every relationship must be founded on well spelt -out intentions from the persons involved as this is what dictates the nature of the relationship. Quite a number of believers have gotten into some relationships where the intent and purpose were not defined only to realize that it is a toxic one.
      It has been revealed that a romantic relationship is the most abused form of relationship simply because of the misconception and faulty mindset that people have sustained over time concerning it. This is not far -fetched from why there have been broken homes, divorces in recent times. According to the National Bureau of Statistics, in 2018 a total of 3,000 divorce cases were recorded in Lagos State. Also in 2019, over 100,000 cases of divorce were recorded in another state.
      The original purpose of God for instituting marriage is essential to expand the governing influence of His kingdom through the family unit on earth. In essence, the state of the society is typically a reflection of its homes. This is why the issue of relationships should not be taken lightly as it has an enormous impact on society.
      </value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1 a.	Discuss the forms of relationships that exists among people
      b.	“Evil company corrupts good manners”. Justify.
      2	Discuss practical ways of keeping and maintaining quality and healthy relationships.
      3	With practical examples, what are the dangers of undefined relationships.
      4 a.	Discuss the various misconceptions that people have concerning romantic relationships.
      b.	What is God’s ordained purpose for;
     i.	Courtship
     ii.	Romantic relationship/Marriage
      5.	Despite the awareness of God’s purpose concerning courtship, marriage and other forms of relationship, discuss why believers still make (the) mistake(s).
     i.	In courtship
     ii.	Of getting into ungodly relationships
     iii.	Of unhealthy relationships
      6 a.	Discuss the following roles of the members of the family respectively (Colossians 3:18-21)
      -> Father (1Tim 3:3-5)
      -> Protector of the family
      -> Provider
      -> Priest
      -> Nourisher
      -> Leader
      -> Builder
      -> Teacher
      -> Loving his wife (1Cor 7:3)
      -> Mother (Eph 5:22)
      -> Support to the family
      -> Submission to the father
      -> Unconditional love
      -> Motherhood (Children upbringing)
      -> Children (1 Tim 5:4)
      -> Obedience
      -> Submission
      -> Honor and respect
      -> Taking up responsibilities and helping out
      6 b.	With practical examples, how can a child be brought up in the way of the Lord in this 21st century.</value>
      <value column="6">Having understood the original intent of God for every form of relationship, it is imperative for us as believers to start gathering the body of truth in matters that concern relationships in every regard. This is needful because it is a major tool God uses through believers to impact society.
      </value>
      <value column="7">How is your relationship impacting the society?
      </value>
      <value column="8" null="true">Do not be unequally yoked together with unbelievers. For what fellowship has righteousness with lawlessness? And what communion has light with darkness?
      </value>
      <value column="9" type="2">O Lord, help me </value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">14</value>
      <value column="1">The Church and the Society: Invading the System</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">Matt 28:18-20, 5:14-16, Acts 1:8
      </value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To understand what the systems of this world mean.; To understand the roles of a believer in coordinating the systems of this world; To understand heaven’s desire for the systems of this world
      </value>
      <value column="4" null="true">A system is a group of many members that function together to carry out a task. Systems are therefore different organized groups of functionaries that work independently of each other with the same goal and under the authority of the same body. After the fall of man, the devil took control of strategic spheres of influence in this world and he uses different platforms to influence men negatively. He does this through spiritual government and he ensures that men without the knowledge of God are in control of certain important spheres of influence so that they can corrupt or tamper with the agenda of God on earth. 
      As long as the structures and the infrastructures of darkness gain pre -eminence, it will be hard for the will of God to be effected on earth. Hence, there is a need for kingdom -minded individuals to penetrate the systems of this world and implement the culture of God in every sphere. Salvation is not all that there is; replicating the ways of the kingdom on earth is the major assignment of every saint - this is what invading the systems is all about.</value>
      <value column="5" null=" true">1) What are the systems of this world and who is in charge? 
      Matt 4:8-9, 2 Cor 4:4, John 8:44,
      2) “The 7 mountains of human influence (Family, Media, Arts and Entertainment, Religion, Government, Education, Economy) are largely controlled by the systems of darkness” how can we justify this? 
      Eze 28:11-19, Rev 18:1-3, 9-13
      3) Does a believer have any authority to challenge the gates of hell (systems of this world)?
      Matt 16:18-19, Phil 2:9-11, Matt 28:18-20

     b. What are God’s intentions for the earth and his people? 
      1Timothy 2:3-4, 1Pet 2:9, Isaiah 60:2, Habakkuk 2:14
      4) How can believers invade the systems of this world and sustain the knowledge of God therein? 

     a. Vision, burden and the understanding of where to penetrate.
      John 5:19, Habakkuk 2:1-3, Nehemiah 2:1-8, John 3:27-30, 1 Cor 1:17

     b. Prayer and demonstration of power.
      1 Cor 4:20, 2:4, James 5:16-18, 2 kings 7:1, 18, Psalm 110:3

     c. Greater Light, skills, wisdom and results
      Isaiah 60:1-3, Matt 5:14-16, Prov 22:29, Dan 1:3-4, 19-20, 2:46-49, 1 Cor 1:25-28

     d. Purity and consecration 
      John 17:17-19, 1 Tim 4:12, 15, John 14:30

     e. Unity and Love of the body Christ 
      John 17:21, 1 Pet 1:22, John 13:35

      </value>
      <value column="6">It is not enough to talk about invading the systems; what are you doing to ensure that light shines in darkness? Do you have the burden, vision and understanding it takes to penetrate the systems? It is also not enough for the church to know what to do. She must be thoroughly equipped and prepared for it. Bible study without action is an effort in futility, don’t take this for granted. God is going to use you - understand where you will take for God and do everything it takes until Christ is seen.
      </value>
      <value column="7">If you refuse to shine your light, darkness will dominate. The brightness of your light will displace darkness if you put it on by the Spirit</value>
      <value column="8" null="true">“Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father which is in heaven.”
      - Matt 5:16</value>
      <value column="9" null="true">I receive grace to focus on what God wants me to do in my generation. I will bring the perspective of God’s kingdom in the sphere God places me in. I’m strengthened for exploits in Jesus name. Amen.</value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">15</value>
      <value column="1">The Church and the Society: Agents of National Transformation</value>

      <value column="2" null="true">Isa 60:1-7 
      </value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To know what National transformation means
              ; To know who an agent of transformation is
              ; To learn about elements of transformation and their effects </value>
      <value column="4" null="true">National Transformation is a change in the administrative structure of a country’s economy, politics, government and all other sectors of power and influence to bring about national development. On the other hand, agents of transformation are instruments (that is, men) with a primary vision to birth forth change. 
            Transformation can either be for a good or evil cause. However, our focus is centred on positive transformation. God made us understand that we are the light of the world (Matt 5:14) and we (agents) should arise and shine for the time that has come (Isaiah 60:1). It is therefore a clarion call for every believer to take their rightful place in bringing about the positive transformation our society needs.
          National transformation is an agenda that can only be achieved by men of authority and power (Luke 10:19). It is not for mere men to float this cause, hence the need for us believers to consciously build the capacity and competence that this course demands. 
          It is the responsibility of the church (You and I) to arise and be properly equipped both on our knees and skills (Daniel). For this reason, national transformation can only be pioneered best by believers if only we deem it fit to be well prepared enough in our various mountains of influence. 
      </value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1a) Who is an Agent of National Transformation?
       b. Can prayers alone transform any Nation? Yes/No (Give reasons)
       c. How can we as believers bring about National Transformation?
        2a) Explain what you understand by “THE MIND, A GATE TO TRANSFORMATION.”
            (Prov 4:23, Rom 12:1-2)
       b. What are the mind control systems that Christians can adopt and how can they be harnessed to bring about national transformation?
        3) Discuss the following tools for National development:
       a. Prayers - Dan 9:2-4
       b. Faith – 1 Sam 17:45
       c. Wisdom and Understanding – Prov 4:7-8, 1Kings 3:9, 12 
       d. Skills – Prov 18:16, Exo 35:35
       e. Competency and Mastery – Dan 1:3-4, 17, 19-20, 1Sam 16:16, 18 
        4) Explain the following traits and qualities of Kingdom Ambassadors.
       a. Fruit of the Spirit (Gal 5:22)
       b. Patriotism - 2Sam 11:8,11 , 2Sam 23:14 – 17.
       c. Servant Leader – Mark 9:35, Luke 22:24 - 27
       d. Integrity – Dan 6:4, Genesis 39:6
       e. Accountability – Luke 18:10, Luke 19:17
       f. Relational Skills  - 1Kings 5:12
       g. Communication Skills – Acts 18:24, Acts 26:24-28, Acts 7:54, 6:10 
       h. Courage and Selflessness – Esth 4:16b
      </value>
      <value column="6">Transformation is a function of light and believers are the Light of the world. Whenever the righteous is in a place of authority, the people rejoice. To sustain the peace, growth, advancement of our Nation, You and I need to rise up to a place of influence where the values of the kingdom can be established. 
      </value>
      <value column="7">Transformation is inside out. You can only reflect what you have become!!!</value>
      <value column="8" null="true"> “When the righteous are in authority, the people rejoice: but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourn.” - Prov 29:2</value>
      <value column="9" null="true">I AM A KINGDOM AMBASSADOR
        I ARISE AND SHINE BECAUSE MY LIGHT IS COME
        I BRING LIGHT AND CHANGE TO EVERY SPHERE I FIND MYSELF
        I AM AN AGENT OF TRANSFORMATION
        A JOY OF MANY GENERATIONS 
        THAT IS WHO I AM</value>
    </row>
    <row>
      <value column="0">16</value>
      <value column="1">The Church and the Society: Sustaining  Kingdom influence and impacts</value>
      <value column="2" null="true">2 Tim 2:1-2, Gen 18:18-19
      </value>
      <value column="3" null="true">To make us understand how the values of the kingdom can be sustained across generations.;To enable us to understand what we mean by kingdom influence and impact.
            ; To make us understand the essence of sustaining the values of the kingdom trans -generationally.
      </value>
      <value column="4" null="true">Kingdom Influence is a way of intentionally imparting a given community/society with the values of the kingdom to reflect the purpose of God for that particular society. In other words, it is the reflection of the virtues and lifestyle of Christ, first in our lives as believers and then to the world at large.
          Sustainable kingdom influence is the preservation and continuity of the culture, beliefs, character, values and ordinances of the kingdom in the lives of individuals which are reflective in the society (2 Tim 2:2). It is first an individual commitment to imbibe as a lifestyle the cardinal values and conform to the ordinances of the kingdom before it can be imparted to others who will as well pass it on to succeeding generations.
          Have you ever wondered why a particular generation would have a heightened wave of God’s move only for it to wane out in the next generation? This is often due to the failure on the part of the predecessors to intentionally pass on the core values of the Kingdom through proper mentorship and constructive teachings to the succeeding generations. It can also be due to a lack of discernment and proper understanding of the concept of succession on the part of the succeeding generations in perpetuating the ordinances of God across generations. 
          Knowing how sensitive succession is in perpetuating the influence of the kingdom on earth across generations, it is therefore imperative of every believer to not only have as a lifestyle the cardinal values and morals of the kingdom but to also intentionally pass it on to the next generation as this is the true definition of success from God’s perspective.</value>
      <value column="5" null="true">1a. In your understanding, what does it mean to sustain kingdom influence?
          b. Explain the following ordinances and values to be sustained across generations:
          i. The Gospel - Rom 1:16-17, 1 Cor 15:1-4, Acts 1:8, Matt 28:19-20
          ii. Sound Doctrine – Titus 2:1, 2 Tim 1:13
          iii. Faith (our tenets as believers) - Jude 1:3-4
          iv. Dominion Mandate – Genesis 1:26-28, Psa 72:8
          v. Strong Character – 2 Pet 1:5-7
        2. Explain the following as the ways through which the aforementioned values can be passed on to the succeeding generations:
          i. Godly Parenting – 2 Tim 1:5, 3:14-15, Genesis 18:19
          ii. Proper mentorship and Discipleship – 1 Sam 22:1-2, 23:8-10, 2 Tim 2:2, Acts 18:24-27, Deut 3:28, 1 Cor 4:15
          iii. Constructive teaching – John 21:17, Jer 3:15, Eph 4:11-14
          iv. Consciously living an exemplary life – Matt 5:16, 1 Tim 4:13, 2 Thess 3:7-9
        3. From your perspective, why do people fall out of the values they’ve been imparted with?
      </value>
      <value column="6">God desires that His influence will not just last a generation but will be passed on across generations. In lieu of this, it is important we understand that kingdom values must first be imbibed as core personal values before we can influence the society with them.
      </value>
      <value column="7">The success of a predecessor lies in the success of his successor.</value>
      <value column="8" null="true">And the things which thou hast heard of me among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithful men, who shall be able to teach others also.” - 2 Tim 2:2</value>
      <value column="9" type="2">Dear Lord, help me to hold on steadfastly to your values, to influence my society with them and pass them on to generations to come.</value>
    </row>
  </rows>
</table>
